Mss.B.T45,T45.1 Mss.B.T45
American Philosophical Society
William Tilghman papers, 1771-1838
Mss.B.T45
American Philosophical Society
58.0 Item(s) 1 Volume
1 volumes; 61 items.
William Tilghman (1756-1827; APS 1805) was a jurist and chief justice of the Pennsylvania Supreme Court. He held several positions as a judge and lawyer in the Philadelphia area and was active in the American Philosophical Society. He helped form and served as the head of the Committee of History, the Moral Sciences and General Literature for the APS and was elected the President of the APS in 1824, a position he held until his death.
Tilghman, William, 1756-1827
Box 1
Volume 1
Scope and Contents note
These papers include letters on business and legal affairs, sales of land, payment of taxes, court sittings, and Dr. S. Bouchell. Also included is a volume of check stubs for expenditures from Tilghman's estate (1827-1838).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased and accessioned, 1958 (1958 1364ms). See in-house shelf list for additional accession numbers.
Biographical/Historical note
William Tilghman (1756-1827; APS 1805) was a jurist and chief justice of the Pennsylvania Supreme Court. He held several positions as a judge and lawyer in the Philadelphia area and was active in the American Philosophical Society. He helped form and served as the head of the Committee of History, the Moral Sciences and General Literature for the APS and was elected the President of the APS in 1824, a position he held until his death.
William Tilghman was born in 1756 in Talbot County, Maryland, to James and Anna (Francis) Tilghman. James Tilghman was a lawyer and Maryland Assembly member, and later secretary of the proprietary land office in Philadelphia. Having graduated from the College of Philadelphia (now the University of Pennsylvania) in 1772, William Tilghman read law with Benjamin Chew until the onset of the Revolution in 1776.
During the Revolution, the Tilghman family was split. William’s older brother, Trench Tilghman, supported the Revolution, joined the Continental Army and was promoted to Washington’s aid-de-camp until the end of the war. A younger brother, Philemon Tilghman, joined the British Navy, married a daughter of Admiral Milbanke, and moved to England after the war. William’s father benefited from several appointments from the Royal government, and remained loyal, choosing to live quietly on his estate in Talbot County Maryland. William also quietly lived in Maryland, finishing his education, focusing primarily on law and classical literature, during the Revolution.
In 1783 Tilghman was admitted to the practice of law in Maryland. From 1788 to 1790 he served as a member of the Maryland Assembly and was a delegate to the Maryland convention to ratify the federal Constitution. He then moved to Philadelphia in 1791, where he was admitted to the bar and married Margaret Elizabeth. In 1801 John Adams appointed Tilghman chief justice of the third circuit court, one of the “Midnight Judges,” Adams appointed at the end of his administration. Tilghman returned to private practice after this court was abolished in 1802. In 1805 he was appointed president judge of the court of common pleas for the area including and surrounding Philadelphia. This same year he was appointed to the Pennsylvania high court of errors and appeals. In 1806 he was commissioned chief justice of the Pennsylvania Supreme Court, a position he held until his death. William Tilghman was elected to the American Philosophical Society in 1805. He helped form, and served as the chairman for, the Committee of History, the Moral Sciences and General Literature. In 1816 he was elected Vice President of the APS and in 1824 he was elected president, a position he held until his death three years later.
Tilghman was a member of the Philadelphia Society for Promoting Agriculture. As a proponent of the development of home industry, he refused, during the last ten years of his life, to wear any garments not made in the United States. Starting in 1802 he was a trustee of the University of Pennsylvania. He was an early proponent of canals connecting the Susquehanna and Alleghany rivers. He died in Philadelphia in 1827.
Early American History Note
This collection consists of two different holdings. B.T45.2 is a small, bound volume that contains receipts from his checkbook. The second part of the collection is slightly richer and contains correspondence and receipts relating to the Tilghman family’s various business interests. Land holdings and legal proceedings are discussed. Most of the correspondence dates to before 1800.
Bouchell, S.; Drinker, Henry, 1734-1809; Goldsborough, Robert; Goldsborough, William; Lloyd, Richard; Meade, George, 1741-1808; Tilghman, Richard; Business Records and Accounts; Check stubs.; Courts.; General Correspondence; Land and Speculation; Law; Law.; Legal Records
- Papers, 1771-1837; Tilghman, William, 1756-1827
  Scope and Contents note
  D. 58 items and one volume. Various sizes.
  - Bond to John Cadwalader, Oct. 21, 1771; Chaires, John
    A.D. 1p. with seal
  - Concerning a bond owned by John FauntLeRoy, sold to Edward Tilghman, June, 1778; 13-1/4x8-1/4; Goldsborough, Robert, 1733-1788
    A.D.S. 2p.and end.with certifications signed by John FauntLeRoy and Joseph Bowley. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, Aug. 19, 1784; 7-3/4x6-1/4; Bonchell, S.
    Bohemia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Can pay one bond in silver. Refers to Abel James.
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Chester, Sept. 8, 12, 1784; 7-3/4x6-1/4; Bonchell, S.
    Bohemia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Concerning money forwarded to pay a bill.
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Chester Town, Md., Sept. 9, 1784; 12-1/2x8; Drinker, Henry, 1734-1809
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business matters.
  - Promissory note to Edward Tilghman, Jan. 14, 1785; 6x7-1/4; Banthram, Lewis
    D.S.: Attest: Rich.Tilghman. 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Power of attorney to William Tilghman, Feb. 5, 1785; 12-3/4x8; Drinker, Henry, 1734-1809
    D.S. Witnessed: Thos.Ewing and Robert Anderson. Certified by Thos.Van Dyke. 2p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, Chester Town, March 28, 1785; 8x6-1/4; Bonchell, S.
    Bohemia, A.L.S. 1p.and add., end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Is sending payment for debts.
  - Letter to Wil[lia]m Tilghman, Chester Town, Md., Aug. 1, 1785; 8x6-1/2; Bonchell, S.
    Bohemia, A.L.S. 1p.and add., end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Will send money on debt.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, Dec. 1, 1785; 7-1/2x6; Bonchell, S.
    Bohemia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business matters.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, Dec. 5, 1785; 3-1/2x7-1/2; Hubey, William
    A.L.S. 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Has deposited money for him.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, Dec. 5, 1785; 4x8-1/4; Hubey, William
    A.L.S. 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Account of money to William Tilghman, Jan. 6, April 19, 1786; Hubey, William
    A.D.S. 3 leaves. Various sizes. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, Chester Town, Md., April 3, 1786; 7-1/4x6-1/4; Bonchell, S.
    A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Letter to W[illiam] Tilghman, April 8, 1786; 8-1/2x8-1/4; Hubey, William
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, May 2, 1786; 9-1/4x8; Hubey, William
    A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Concerning business of Mr.Drinker.
  - Memorandum of the settlement of Benjamin Wilke's bond, June 2, 1786; 13-1/4x7-3/4; Hubey, William
    A.D.S. 1p.and end.by William Tilghman. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, Sept. 30, 1786; 5x8-1/4; Hubey, William
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, Nov. 13, 1786; 6x6; Hubey, William
  - Bill of cost for W[illia]m Tilghman, June 12, 1787; 3-1/4x7-1/2; Earle, James, Sir, 1755-1817
    A.D.S. 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.) For court costs for a case.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, April 29, 1788; 4x7-1/4; Tilghman, Richard
    A.L.S. 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Concerning a court case.
  - Letter to Simon Wilmer and William Tilghman, May 14, 15, 1788; 13-1/4x8; Ricketts, John Thomas
    Chestertown, Md.; Big Elk, Md., A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business of a law suit.
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Chester Town, Aug. 14, 1789; 12-1/2x7-1/2; Bauldon, Jacob
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see William Tilghman papers.) Concerning some real estate.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, March 26, 1790; 4-1/4x6-1/2; Keene, John Y.
    Long Marsh, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Letter to William Tilghman, April 8, 1790; 8-1/4x6-1/2; Thompson, Richard
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p.and add.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Asks him to care for a law suit.
  - Receipt to William Tilghman, Jan., 1791; 3x8-1/2; Vansant, John. Trustees
    D. 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Letter to William Tilghman, March 5, 1791; 13-1/4x8-1/4; Porter, Benjamin
    A.D.S.: Benja[min] Porter for Rebecca Price. 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Pertaining to the estate of Joseph Price.
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Philadelphia, July 6, 1795; 9-1/4x8; Scott, James
    Chester, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Sept. 21, 1795; 9-1/4x8; Scott, James
    Chester, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, Nov. 18, 1795; 7-3/4x4-1/2; Gibbs, Joshua W.
    L.in 3rd.P.: J.W.and W.Gibbs. 1p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Nov. 23, 1795; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Gibbs, Joshua W.
    L.S.: Josh.W.and Wm.Gibbs. 1p.and add., end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Memorandum of Messrs. Joshua W. and William Gibbs proposal, Nov. 25, 1795; 7x5; Tilghman, William, 1756-1827
    A.D.S.with initials. 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Philadelphia, Sept. 10, 1796; 9-1/4x7-1/2; Scott, James
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Philadelphia, Oct. 9, 1796; 9-1/4x7-1/2; Scott, James
    A.L.S. 5p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Concerning unfinished legal business.
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Feb. 12, 1798; 8-3/4x8; Field, John
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Philadelphia, May 4, 1798; 9-1/4x7-3/4; Scott, James
    A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Concerning the collection of debts through legal action.
  - Receipt to John Lare, jr. on account of William Tilghman, Dec. 10, 1800; 3-1/2x8-1/4; Watson, William
    A.D.S.: W[illia]m Watson for James Watson 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Letter to William Tilghman, April 1, 1801; 9x7-1/4; Meade, George, 1741-1808
    A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business. Friendly letter.
  - Receipt to John Lare, jr. on account of W[illia]m Tilghman, Feb. 18, 1802; 3x7; Wilson, William
    A.D.S.: W[illia]m Wilson for James Wilson 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.)
    Not Found: 2/7/2011
  - Receipts to Fr[e]d[eric]k Beisel for William Tilghman, Nov.-Dec., 1803; 5x8; Wilson, James
    A.D.S. 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Agreement with John Handshoe's Estate for the sale of land, June 20, 1808; Tilghman, William, 1756-1827
    D.S.: Wm.Tilghman and two others. Witnessed. 1p. On same sheet is agreement of sale of same land to Jacob Mock(?); Dec. 14, 1808. 1p. (see Tilghman papers.)
    Item previously cataloged as: T45.1 No. 1.
  - Calculations on a bond due, July 15, 1810; 4x8; Tilghman, William, 1756-1827
  - Letter to William Goldsborough, Frederick Town, Maryland, June 23, 1813; Tilghman, William, 1756-1827
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Tilghman Papers.) Concerning the Coxe family's land claims.
    Item previously cataloged as: T45.1 No. 2.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, Philadelphia, March 13, 1819; 10x8; Saeger, Daniel & Jacob
    L. 1p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Promise to pay William Tilghman, April 9, 1821; 3-1/2x8; Grosshof, James
  - Letter to Richard Lloyd, Providence, Penna., Aug. 6, 1821
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see Tilghman Papers.) Is satisfied with his statement. Will write when he returns from the west.
    Item previously cataloged as: T45.1, no. 3
  - Monies paid for road taxes, Dec. 12, 1821; 12-3/4x8; Tilghman, William, 1756-1827
    D. 1p.and end. Receipted by G. Hewitt and R.H. Rose. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Letter to Bishop [William] White, July 18, 1825; Tilghman, William, 1756-1827
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Tilghman Papers.) Gives his opinion on church matters.
    Item previously cataloged as: T45.1 No.4
  - List and account of articles taken by James Tilghman, May 18, 1827; 8-1/4x8-1/4; Tilghman, William. Estate
    D. Certified by Will[ia]m Baker. 1p. and end. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Account book, 1827-1837; B T45.2; 1.0 vol. (Volume 1)
    General note
    Not found 5/2011
    Account book showing expenses, 1827-1837, and blank pages.
  - Letters to Samuel [Rowland] Fisher, Philadelphia, April 23-May 3, 1831-1845; 16-3/4x13; Payne, John
    London, L.S.: John Payne and Samuel Spackman. 9p.and end. Copies. (see William Tilghman papers.) Concerning the settlement of Henry Drinker's estate.
  - Receipt to the estate of William Tilghman, July 21, 1835; 4x8; Elliott, Isaac
    D.S. 1p. (see William Tilghman papers.)
  - Check to Mr. Keslin, March 28, 1837; 2-1/2x6-1/2; Price, Eli K. (Eli Kirk), 1797-1884
    Philadelphia, Printed D.filled in in ms.S. 1p.and end. (see William Tilghman paper
  - Letter to [William Tilghman]., Undated; 7-3/4x6-1/4; Bonchell, S.
    A.L.S. 1p. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Undated; 13x7-1/4; Bouldon, Jacob
    Chester Town. A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Tilghman, Chester Town, Undated; 8x6-1/4; Cooke, W.
    Sunday morning. A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Letter to William Tilghman, Undated; 12-1/2x8; Cooke, W.
    Chester Town. A.L.S. 2p.,add.,end. (see William Tilghman papers.) Business.
  - Copy of Mr. Tilghman's bill, Undated
    A.D. 1p.
  - Letter to Edward S. Burd, Undated; Tilghman, William, 1756-1827
    Monday, A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see Tilghman Papers.) Must refuse invitation, since court is sitting.